International Ladies Garment Workers Union. Schlesinger, Benjamin, President. Records, 1914-1923. 5780/009
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies Garment Workers Union. Benjamin Schlesinger, President. Records
1914-1923.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Schlesinger, Benjamin, 1876-1932
5780/009
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Correspondence and subject files.
Correspondence, form letters, circulars and subject files relating to Schlesinger's second term as president, June 1914 to January 1923. Topics covered in these materials include union organizing; strikes, labor disputes, working conditions, and other labor issues in the women's garment industry, particularly in New York City; inter-union relations; relations between manufacturers' associations and the union; efforts by Schlesinger and others to form an alliance of garment workers' unions; discussions with foreign garment workers' unions; education for workers in New York City; and Jewish war relief efforts during World War I.
3833854
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Robert E. Lazar and David Banush
Date completed:
August 1999
EAD encoding:
Casey S. Westerman, June 2002
Biographical / Historical
Benjamin Schlesinger was born December 25, 1876, in Krakai, Lithuania, in what was then Russia, the son of Nechemiah and Judith Schlesinger, and attended the local Cheyder. His grandfather, Simcha, was Rabbi in Racinn, Lithuania. His father died when he was four and his mother some years later in 1909. He emigrated with an older brother to this country in 1891, settling in Chicago, and became an American citizen in that city on March 19, 1898. He was married to Rose Schenhause on August 27, 1899 in Chicago.
Schlesinger's first job after his arrival in Chicago was peddling matches but, a few weeks later, he was employed as a "floor boy" in a cloak shop. Two years later, when he was 17, and a sewing machine operator on ladies' cloaks and suits, he led his first strike, a successful one, in his shop. He was a delegate from Chicago to the convention, held at 125 Rivington Street, New York City, which founded the International Cloak Makers Union of America on May 1, 1892. Schlesinger, then only 16 years old, was elected treasurer. In 1895 he was elected recording secretary of the Chicago Cloak Makers Union, a post he held for at least three years. He became business manager and organizer of Local 5 of the Chicago Cloakmakers' Union in 1902 and, when the five Chicago locals united under a Joint Executive Board, he became manager of that organization.
In May 1903, Schlesinger was elected president of the ILGWU and, after only a brief term, became organizer for the New York locals in January 1904, in which post he stayed until 1907. For the period 1907 to 1912, he served as manager of the New York Jewish Daily Forward; while still in that position, he served as a member of the Strike Committee in the 1910 strike and later was appointed a member of the Board of Grievances (1911).
In June 1914, Schlesinger was once more elected president of the ILGWU and served until January 1923. During this period, other offices he held included the following: manager of the New York Joint Board, "without pay, temporarily," (1914); president, Needle Trades Workers Alliance (1920); member, general executive board, International Clothing Workers' Federation, Amsterdam (1919-23); delegate, American Federation of Labor, to British Trades Union Congress (1922); and member, People's Relief Committee (1917-22). Schlesinger served (1923-28) as manager of the Chicago office of the Jewish Daily Forward and was elected, for the last time, as president of the ILGWU in October 1928, serving until his death in June 1932. Benjamin Schlesinger was, at various times, a member of the Workmen's Circle, Forward Association, Socialist Labor Party and Socialist Party.
Among the proposals which Benjamin Schlesinger initiated and which were then or later adopted as policy by the Union, were the following: he introduced at the convention of 1902 a resolution urging locals to arrange bimonthly or at least monthly lectures and discussions on all educational subjects. At the 1903 convention, he introduced a resolution urging locals to establish sick-benefit funds. In 1914, he proposed special training of active workers for the Union and the International entered into an arrangement with the Rand School of Social Science for a course of studies for members of the New York locals. The program lasted for one year. The following year, June 28, 1915, in the midst of demonstrations and strike demands on the question of "hiring and firing," Schlesinger asked the Protective Association to submit the dispute to a committee of unbiased persons. As a result a Council of Conciliation was appointed by Mayor Mitchel and the strike was avoided. Another strike in Chicago that same summer was similarly avoided. In 1918, he successfully proposed that business agents be considered "experts" and appointed by the elected officers. He was also successful, in the period 1920-21, in dividing Local 25 into two groups of waistmakers and dressmakers, to accommodate the growing dressmaking section of the industry, resulting in the establishment of the New York Dress Makers' Union, Local 22, then the largest local union in the International. On July 1, 1920, Schlesinger addressed a letter to the Neckwear Workers' Union of New York, the International Journeymen Tailors' Union of America, the International Fur Workers' Union, the United Garment Workers of America, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the United Cloth Hat, Cap Makers and Millinery Workers' Union of America, proposing an alliance of all garment workers unions. Discussions dragged on for several years but with only limited success. On November 15, 1921, Schlesinger laid the cornerstone of a new building at 3 W. 16th Street, NYC, which served as the union's General Office until it moved into 1710 Broadway in 1943.
He was the author of several pamphlets on the garment industry. He died on June 6, 1932. In 1967, the junior high school on New York Blvd., Jamaica, Queens, was named the Benjamin Schlesinger Junior High School in his honor.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, form letters, circulars and subject files relating to Schlesinger's term, June 1914 to January 1923. Topics covered in these materials include union organizing; strikes, labor disputes, working conditions, and other labor issues in the women's garment industry, particularly in New York City; inter-union relations; relations between manufacturers' associations and the union; efforts by Schlesinger and others to form an alliance of garment workers' unions; discussions with foreign garment workers' unions; education for workers in New York City; and Jewish war relief efforts during World War I.
Individuals and organizations represented in the general correspondence file include: Jane Addams; American Medical Aid for Russia; the American Red Cross; Abraham Baroff; Joseph Barondess; Bernard Braff; Robert Bruère; the Cloak, Suit & Skirt Manufacturer's Association; Max Danish; Clarence S. Darrow; Israel Feinberg; John Fitzpatrick of the Chicago Federation of Labor; J.J. Goldman; Adolph Held; Henry Hilfers; Sidney Hillman; Hamilton Holt; Humanitarian Cult; Isaac A. Hourwich; Fiorello H. LaGuardia; Algernon Lee; Jean Longuet; Judah L. Magnes; Amos Pinchot; Norman Thomas; Alexander Trachtenberg; B.C. Vladeck; Lillian Wald; Stephen Wise; and the Women's Trade Union League.
Significant organizations, individuals and topics represented in the subject files include AFL officials, including letters from Samuel Gompers and Frank Morrison; the British Trades Union Congress; letters from Abraham Cahan of the Jewish Daily Forward; correspondence from Morris Hillquit on union legal matters; and materials on the International Clothing Workers' Federation.
Other organizations and individuals in the subject files include letters from Louis Marshall; the Mayor's Council of Conciliation in the Cloak & Suit Industry (New York City); United Garment Workers' Union of America; United Ladies' Tailors Trade Union (London, England); United Mine Workers; United Textile Workers; letters from Samuel Untermyer; the Waterproof Garment Manufacturers' Association; and the Wholesale Dress Manufacturers' Association.
The subject files also contain considerable documentation of numerous locals of the International, including Local 8 (San Francisco Cloak Makers' Union), Local 21 (Chicago Cloak Cutters' Union), Local 22 (Dressmakers' Union), Local 23 (Skirt and Cloth Dressmakers' Union), Local 25 (Ladies' Waist and Dressmakers Union), Local 28 (Ladies' Garment Workers, Seattle), Local 30 (Cutters and Trimmers of Cincinnati), Local 32, (Winnipeg, Manitoba), Local 33 (Corset Workers' Union), Local 34 (Corset Cutters Union), Local 35 (Cloak, Skirt and Dress Pressers' Union), Local 37 (Pressers' Union), Local 38 (Ladies' Tailors' and Dressmakers' Union), Local 39-40 (Corset Workers' Union), and Local 41 (Wrapper, Kimono and House Dress Makers' Union).
Other locals represented include Local 43 (Ladies' Waist and White Goods Workers' Union), Local 44 (Chicago Cloakmakers' Union), Local 45 (National Alliance of Ladies' Cloaks and Suits Designers), Local 48 (Italian Cloak, Suit and Skirtmakers' Union), Local 49 (Waist, Dress and Petticoat Workers' Union), Local 50 (Misses and Children's Dressmakers' Union), and Local 52 (Los Angeles).
Related Materials
5780/002. David Dubinsky. President's records, 1932-1966.
5780/010. Benjamin Schlesinger. President's records, 1928-1932.
5780/056. Research Department records, 1907-1948, 1910-1940 (bulk).
Arrangement
Correspondence and subject files are alphabetically arranged within each section.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions; Women's clothing industry -- United States; Women's clothing industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing trade -- United States; Clothing trade -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- United States; Clothing workers -- New York (State) -- New York; Strikes and lockouts -- Clothing trade -- New York (State) -- New York; Strikes and lockouts -- Clothing trade -- United States; Labor disputes -- New York (State) -- New York; Labor disputes -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Industrial relations -- New York (State) -- New York; Working class -- Education -- New York (State) -- New York; World War, 1914-1918 -- Civilian relief; Correspondence; Organization files; Form letters; Circulars; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Addams, Jane, 1860-1935.; Baroff, Abraham.; Barondess, Joseph.; Braff, Bernard.; Bruère, Robert W. (Robert Walter), 1876-1964.; Cahan, Abraham, 1860-1951.; Danish, Max D.; Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938.; Feinberg, Israel.; Fitzpatrick, John.; Goldman, J. J.; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Held, Adolph.; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946.; Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933.; Holt, Hamilton, 1872-1951.; Hourwich, Isaac Aaronovich, 1860-1924.; LaGuardia, Fiorello H.(Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947.; Lee, Algernon.; Longuet, Jean.; Magnes, Judah Leon, 1887-1948.; Marshall, Louis, 1856-1929.; Morrison, Frank, 1859-1949.; Pinchot, Amos, 1873-1944.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Trachtenberg, Alexander.; Untermyer, Samuel, 1858-1940.; Vladeck, Baruch Charney, 1886-1935.; Wald, Lillian D., 1867-1940.; Wise, Stephen S.; American Federation of Labor; American Medical Aid for Russia (Organization); American National Red Cross.; Cloak, Suit and Skirt Manufacturers' Protective Association (New York, N.Y.); Humanitarian Cult (Organization); International Clothing Workers' Federation; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union--Presidents.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 5 (Chicago, Ill.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 8 (San Francisco, Calif.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 21 (Chicago, Ill.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 22 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 23-25 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 28 (Seattle, Wash.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 30 (Cincinnati, Ohio); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 32 (Winnipeg, Man.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 33 (Bridgeport, Conn.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 34 (Bridgeport, Conn.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 35 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 37 (Cleveland, Ohio); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 38 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 39-40 (New Haven, Conn.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 41 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 43 (Worcester, Mass.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 44 (Chicago, Ill.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 45 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 48 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 49 (Boston, Mass.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 50 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 52 (Los Angeles, Calif.); New York (N.Y.).Mayor's Council of Conciliation in the Cloak and Suit Industry; Trades Union Congress.; United Garment Workers of America; United Ladies' Tailors Trade Union; United Mine Workers of America; United Textile Workers; Waterproof Garment Manufacturers' Association; Wholesale Dress Manufacturers' Association; Women's Trade Union League; Forṿerṭs (New York, N.Y.)
3833854
- Series I. Correspondence.
  - A., Includes letter from Jane Addams, Aug. 1922; letter notifying Schlesinger on his election to membership on the Organizing Committee for the Peoples Council of America for Democracy and Peace, June 1917; proposed outline from American Civil Liberties Union on relation between employers and workers, July 1921; letters from American Jewish Congress re meetings, 1917. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A., Includes financial requests from American Medical Aid for Russia, 1922; letters from American Red Cross on their campaigns, 1917-18; correspondence with Misha Appelbaum (founder), Humanitarian Cult re:strike in cloak industry and his effort to arbitrate, 1916; letter from Leon Arkin (Jewish Daily Forward), Boston, on union activities in Boston, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B., Includes correspondence with Abraham Baroff, 1919; letters from Joseph Barondess requesting financial assistance for individuals and East Broadway Kehillah 1917-18; correspondence with Arthur Somers (President), Board of Education, NYC, on use of Italian or Yiddish in night courses in public schools, 1918. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - B., Includes two letters from Bernard Braff (Gen. Secretary-Treas.) to Jacob Leibowitz (Member, GEB), 1900-01; Robert W. Bruere's resignation letter from Board of Arbitration in Dress Industry, 1916. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - C., Includes letter from Allen Robinson (chairman), Citizens Committee for the Support of the Locked-Out Cloak and Suit Makers requesting contributions to be used for settling differences between manufacturers and union and not for strike benefits, July 1916; Schlesinger letter to Cloak, Suit and Skirt Manufacturers Association, stating union's position in adjusting relations between union and manufacturers, May 1922. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - D., Includes memoranda with Max Danish (Editor), Justice, 1917-1918; letters from Clarence S. Darrow, 1917, 1922; letter from Morris Weiss (President), Dress and Waist Manufacturers Association on Garment Industry situation, Jan. 1919. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - E., Includes letters from Educational Alliance, 1918; correspondence with Henry Hilfers (Secretary), Essex Trades Council, 1915, 1918. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - F., Includes letter from D. Feinberg (Secretary), Jewish Colonization Association, on Jewish communities in Europe, Nov. 1915; Israel Feinberg letter of resignation as General Manager from New York Cloak and Dress Joint Board, 1922; correspondence with John Fitzpatrick (President), Chicago Federation of Labor, 1917, 1919-20; John P. Frey (Editor), International. Moulders Union, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - G., Including correspondence with Harry A. Garfield, Fuel Administrator, on order issued on coal consumption (heatless Mondays) and suspension of order, Jan-Feb. 1918; letters from J. J. Goldman (President), Dress and Waist Manufacturers Association, 1916. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - H., Including letters from Adolph Held, Isaac A. Hourwich. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - I., Including Hamilton Holt letter of resignation from Board of Arbitration in Dress and Waist Industry, 1916; letter to International Journeymen Tailors' Union requesting alliance of all garment workers' unions, Jan. 1920; General Executive Board resolution against fascist activities in America, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - J., Including letter from John J. Jennings (business representative), Local 119, Steam and Operating Engineers re: embroidery workers of New Jersey, 1916; letters from Adolph Held, 1917; B.C. Vladeck, Jewish Daily Forward, 1919; correspondence with Jewish organizations for aid, including letter from Jacob Schiff (chairman), Jewish War Relief Committee, 1918; Cyrus L. Sulzberger (chairman), Campaign for Jewish War Sufferers, 1917. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - K., Including letter from Karl Kautsky transmitting article (not enclosed), 1920; letter from George W. Kirchwey (Dean), Columbia University Law School, on plan for conference between union and employers, 1920; Felix Warburg letter on union assistance to War Relief Fund, 1918. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - L-Le., Includes letter from Fiorello H. LaGuardia (Deputy Attorney General, New York) on settling differences between Employers' Association and union 1916. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Li-Lu., Includes letter from Abraham Liessin (Editor), Zukunft, n,d.; correspondence with Jean Longuet (Editor), Le Populaire, 1920-22. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - M., Includes letters from Judah L. Magnes; correspondence with William Morgan (President), Merchants Association of New York, on disturbance incidents during the Waist and Dress Industry strike, Feb. 1919. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - N., Includes correspondence with Norman Thomas (Associate Editor), The Nation, July 1922; letter to Neckwear Workers Union of New York, requesting alliance of all garment workers' unions, July 1920; Moses Oppenheimer letter offering Schlesinger position of business manager for the New Review, October 1912. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - O-Q., Includes letters from Amos Pinchot on military and war matters, 1917. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - R., Includes correspondence with Alexander Trachtenberg (director), Department of Labor Research, Rand School of Social Science, 1916,. 1918; letter from Algernon Lee (education director), Rand School of Social Science, 1922; letters from Morris Rothenberg, union attorney, re: cases, 1919-1921; letter from Sidney Hillman, (president), Russian American Industrial Corporation, on supplying money (capital) to factories in Russia, 1922. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - S. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - T-U., Includes letter from Cyrus Adler, United Synagogue of America, on union activities in Philadelphia. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - W-Z., Includes letters from Lillian Wald, Stephen Wise, 1915; correspondence with New York City Police Commissioner Arthur Woods on police handling of strikes, 1915-1916; letters from Women's Trade Union League on union-related matters, 1914-1918. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II. Subject Files.
  - A. American Federation of Labor, 1914-1923.
    - AFL: 1914., Includes correspondence on placing AFL organizer in Cleveland to aid in organizing cloakmakers. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - AFL: May-July 1915., Correspondence on conflict between union and Cloak Manufacturers' Protective Association, May-June; correspondence re: unions that broke away from United Garment workers of America and activities of United Hebrew Trades and AFL in trying to bring reconciliation in the trade unions, June-July. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - AFL Sept.-Dec. 1915., Includes correspondence on organizing activities; negotiations with manufacturers. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - AFL: Jan-Aug. 1916., Includes correspondence on AFL assisting union during embroidery workers' strike, Hudson County, New Jersey; jurisdictional dispute with United Textile Workers. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - AFL: Sept.-Dec. 1916 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - AFL: Jan-July 1917., Correspondence Union activities, Chicago; manufacturing of military garments in waterproof garment factories, New York (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - AFL: Aug-Dec. 1917., Includes correspondence on government contracts and labor-industrial problems during war. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - AFL: Jan-April 1918., Same as above. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - AFL: May-Dec. 1918., Includes correspondence re strike at firm, Leo F. Strum Co. under contract with Navy Dept.; letter from Santiago Iglesias (President), Free Federation of Workingmen of Puerto Rico, re Governor Arthur Yager of Puerto Rico, 1918. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - AFL: 1919 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - AFL: 1920., Includes correspondence and report, "Profiteering in dress goods and women's garments," May-June. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - AFL: 1921., Includes letter from Charles E. Hughes (Secretary of State) to Samuel Gompers on trade relations between U.S. and Russia, April. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - AFL: 1922-Jan. 1923., Includes correspondence on AFL affiliating with International. Federation of Trade Unions. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - B. Subject Files, A-L.
    - Austrian Tailors Union, 1920. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - British Trades Union Congress. 1922., Benjamin Schlesinger, AFL delegate. Includes Schlesinger address; correspondence with Gompers on AFL affiliating with International. Federation of Trade Unions and being represented at Hague Disarmament Conference, Dec. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Cahan, Abraham., Two letters, 1919, 1922. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Form letters and circulars, 1915-1916. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Form letters and circulars, 1917-1918. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Form letters and circulars, 1919. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Form letters and circulars, 1920. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Form letters and circulars, 1921. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Form letters and circulars, 1922. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hillquit, Morris, 1916-22., Correspondence re: cases, agreements and related Union matters. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - International Clothing Workers Federation, Amsterdam, Holland, 1920., Correspondence with Secretary Van der Heeg on international trade union matters, conferences. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - International Clothing Workers Federation, 1921-1922., Includes correspondence on conditions in Hungarian garment industry; finances. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - C. Locals.
    - Locals 8 and 21 (Cloak and Skirtmakers' Union) 1914-16, 1921-22. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Local 22 (Dressmakers' Union) 1921-22. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Local 23 (Skirt and Cloth Dressmakers' Union) 1915-19, 1922., Includes minutes of meeting between Locals 22 and 23 on re-affiliation, Nov. 1922. (Box 3, Folder 14)